RG 035, Connecticut Office of Price Administration
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Office of Price Administration records
1942-1949
Connecticut State Library
United States. Office of Price Administration. Connecticut Office
14.5 cubic feet
In August 1941, the Federal government set up the Office of Price Administration in order to stabilize prices, obtain optimum production of essential war materials and prevent a post-war price collapse.
RG035
Multiple
Historical Note
The Office of Price Administration (OPA) was a Federal Government agency set up in August 1941 to aid in stabilizing prices, obtaining adequate production of essential items and preventing a post-war price collapse. It operated largely through rationing materials in short supply, establishing price and rent ceilings, and engaging in extensive public information activities. The agency set up nine regional offices, one of which was the New England office located in Boston. The Boston office set up the Connecticut branch office in December 1941, and in May 1942, Chester Bowles, future Connecticut Governor, became its director. The Connecticut office ran a rationing program, established price and rent ceilings, and engaged in various public information activities. Most records of the Connecticut state and local offices appear to have been destroyed. Most Connecticut OPA activity seems to have ceased by the fall of 1945.
Scope and Content
This record group contains a rent survey chart, correspondence, memoranda, press releases, bulletins, speeches and radio scripts, subject files, records of the local Goshen office, and ration card applications for New Milford and New London. It also contains Broadcast scripts and Education Program records.
Related Material
RG 005:029, Raymond E. Baldwin gubernatorial records, 1943-1945 (under "Office of Price Administration", "OPA", etc.)
RG 036, Temporary State Housting Rent Commission, 1942-1946
RG 050, War Council, 1940-1945.
Index Terms
Organizations:
United States. Office of Price Administration. Connecticut Office
Persons:
Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986
Subjects:
Goshen (Conn.); Prices -- Connecticut; Rationing -- Connecticut; United States. Office of Price Administration. Connecticut Office -- Records and correspondence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects
Places:
Goshen (Conn.)
Document Types:
Application forms; Charts; Correspondence; Memorandums; Newsletters; Press releases; Radio scripts
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The State Library applied for the Goshen and West Haven OPA board records on July 30, 1945. On September 26, 1945, Mr. Dunn of the Connecticut OPA, State Headquarters notified Harold Burt, Examiner of Public Records that the board was closing on September 28th and the staff could pick up the records at that time. When T.D. Murphy, Director, War Records Department and Mr. Burt arrived, the OPA's clerk, Miss Phyllis H. Prindle, had taken all of the records out of the filing cases, and had indiscriminately stacked them in cartons of various sizes and shapes. She had taken the forms, correspondence, etc., out the identifying folders, which she evidently intended to destroy. Mr. Murphy, Mr. Burt and Mary West, an assistant in the War Records Department rescued the records. Since the 28th was Miss Prindle's last official day, Mr. Burt and Mr. Murphy did not ask her to return the documents to their original folders. They later attempted to establish some order after transferring the records to the State Library.
Education Programs records and broadcast scripts given by for OPA official Hugo Saglio who served as Radio Officer and Education Services Officer.
Container List
- Records, 1942-1949; 14.5 cubic feet
  - T002689
    - 1. Rent survey charts, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
      Contains tabulation forms ("Reference List of Rated and Inspected Comparables") including original handwritten data concerning rental housing in East Hartford, Norwich, New Britain, West Hartford, Hartford Manchester, Middletown, New London, Bristol and Meriden. The forms list individual housing units with street addresses, type of unit, number of rooms, equipment and services, age of structure, condition, range of rental prices and "freeze date of rent."
    - 2. Information Division general file, 1942-1946
      Contains press releases, bulletins, information sheets and kits, drafts of public information materials and related correspondence and memoranda with miscellaneous material at the end.
      Alphabetical by subject.
      - A-I (Box 2)
      - L-T (Box 3)
      - V-W (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 3. Information Division bulletins, releases and scripts, 1942-1946
      - Weekly Column (District Director), 1942-1946; 1 bundle (Box 5)
      - Bulletins, 1 bundle (Box 5)
      - News Releases, 1942-1946; 5 bundles (Box 5)
      - District Director's Radio Talks, 1 bundle (Box 6)
      - Five-Minute Talks, 4 bundles (Box 6)
        - 1942-1945 (Box 6)
        - 1946 (Box 7)
      - Fifteen-Minute Radio Interviews, 1943-1946; 4 bundles (Box 7)
      - Nan Clarke Radio Show, 1942-1943; 1 folder (Box 7)
      - Una King Radio Show, 1942-1943; 1 folder (Box 7)
      - Jan Miner Radio Show, 1943-1944; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Janet Slayton Radio Show, 1943; 1 folder (Box 7)
    - 4. Goshen Local Board files, 1942-1945
      Contains correspondence, administrative papers, applications for rations and related materials.
      These papers were received by the Library in some disarray and were arranged later by State Library Staff.
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Administrative papers (Box 8)
      - Administrative papers (Box 9)
      - Fuel Oil (Box 9)
      - Fuel Oil (Box 10)
      - Gasoline (Box 10)
      - Gas Ration, A-V (Box 11)
      - Gas Ration, W-Z (Box 12)
      - Tires and Tubes (Box 12)
      - Tires and Tubes (Box 13)
      - Food (Box 13)
      - Footwear (Box 13)
      - Stoves (Box 13)
    - 5. Ration card applications, 1943 (Box 14)
      Form application for ration cards. Listing name and address of applicant and names and birth dates of family members.
      Incomplete files, arranged alphabetically, for New Milford. (A-I) and New London (K-Z).
  - 1992-082
    - Broadcast scripts and Education Program records, 1943-1946 (Box 1)
      RESTRICTED due to condition.
      Unarranged.